Are we solving the right problems?
My heart goes out to patient care 100%.
But my heart goes out to providers 100%.
Because they are the ones in the
interaction leading the care and
building trust and needing to build
trust for adherence, for hope, for
families to have faith.
But it's still an issue that we got to
figure out how to solve for it. It's not
easy. Kam, welcome to the Sigma Room. I
was so excited to have you on. I I think
we've had some really interesting
exchanges over the last couple weeks and
uh it was clear that we there's just a
lot of things that we're we share a
common passion for. So, thank you so
much for agreeing to come on the show.
Yeah, thank you for having me. You know,
I'm I'm really grateful to serendipity
and giving us the opportunity to connect
and finding alignment in in things that
we are passionate about is always
something very exciting and motivating
to to meet others. So, I'm excited to be
here. Well, it's it's been a a really
wonderful career for me having to the
chance to work with with providers and
just being around the interactions
within the healthcare setting. And for
me, it's been really a lot more about
the interactions with between human
beings than it was really is about
anything else. But what's really
probably the most me meaningful to me is
when I have a conversation with someone
like you, you're wired in a way that
everything is all about who the person
that's in front of you who you're taking
care of. And I can't say it enough about
the commitment that it takes to do what
you do. And I really want to dig into
some things today because I know we've
been talking about AI and governance and
a lot of stuff like that. Innovation's
been a thing that's been talked about
forever. digital transformation, you
know, buzzwords are us basically, but
what it really comes down to is are we
doing the right things? Are we solving
the right problems? And I don't know
that we do such a great job with that.
But we're at a point right now things
are moving very, very quickly. So, I
think it's a great opportunity for us to
kind of take a pause and really take a
look at what we're doing and what should
we be doing and and where are there
better opportunities maybe that we're
not paying attention to because we're
distracted. there's a long a long way to
go to say I really would love to hear
you you talk about what's top of mind
for you and if you know if we can tag
team and figure out what one or two
meaningful things we could tackle
together like soon right away bring in
more people whatever what would some of
those things be for you
yeah you know I think thank you again
for the by speaking of my my experiences
you know I think first being a clinician
being a provider in multiple
environments inpatient outpatient
clinics
building a program within a hospital
system and then going and scaling
another business for virtual care.
There's a lot of lenses that as a
provider I was able to see. As an
operator I was able to see and I really
kind of saw things outside the box that
I'm like, "Oh, you know, maybe there's a
solution for this or hey, maybe I can
make this a lot easier for providers
where they get more quality time back,
right?" Like there was always something
in the back of my mind every day I was
in the clinic like thinking how can we
do this how can we do this how can we do
this and I think that we are in a space
and in a time where there is opportunity
to really look at the workflows the huge
admin burden that providers are facing
every day and their staff every day and
my main goal with where I'm at high
level right now is because I've been in
these different systems. I've worked for
a big healthcare company building
clinical programs for very big
companies. There's a lot of line of
sight that we have in immersing
ourselves in these specific
environments.
And my goal would be to utilize and
leverage these amazing technologies when
used correctly, solving the right
problem, filling the gap. And my goal
would be to provide time back to the
human to human interaction. I think a
lot of times we have to remember what
we're doing and who's doing it, right?
Like my heart goes out to patient care
100%. But my heart goes out to providers
100%. because they are the ones in the
interaction leading the care and
building trust and needing to build
trust for adherence, for hope, for
families to have faith. You know, a lot
of times we're focusing on adults. I'm a
pediatric provider and I saw what
happens to families and to parents and
how overwhelming it could be and how
overwhelming it can be for a provider to
string care together. And so there are
opportunities in the wealth of data that
there is. There is a lot of data and for
a provider to put a story together it is
very taxing very taxing when you are
seeing a new patient even if you're
seeing a patient you've been seeing for
years or months whatever it may be there
are opportunities but people who are in
it are able to help you say this is what
I need this is what I want this is where
I wish I could have more time right and
so my experience what I'm trying to do
is add a voice to the people that I
worked with, to the people who were the
warriors taking care of all of the
patients that we were taking care of. I
give all the credit to them in the
worlds that I grew up in. The amount of
compassion and empathy that I learned
from those individuals above me when I
came into the world 25 years ago, to my
peers, to the nurses who taught me, to
the doctors who taught us, there are
amazing people out there taking care of
our people. And so my goal is to utilize
the data, problem solve and analyze it
and provide ways to give back to the
human component. If I'm giving you a
general summary,
you're talking about what's been top of
mind for me as well. And we we have to
think about how do we give time back and
whenever you talk about innovation or AI
things kind of come around to efficiency
inevitably. While you know I understand
that there's a need for an ROI, I think
that there's an intangible that is not
really put into the right category as an
ROI, but it absolutely is. We're we
already we're starting from a place
where there's a deficit.
Yeah,
we have consistently year after year
taken more and more time away from the
patient and the provider encounter. But
even worse, we've crept into an area
where I've had mentioned this term with
a couple of folks recently and Dr. Mark
Zendro told mentioned to me and just
casually you say again in the evening
it's really pajama time. I'm like wait
is that a thing? And when I started to
understand just how far we have crept
into like even family life time where
people should actually be sleeping even
we've gone in the opposite direction and
so giving that time back really is a big
deal but you know maybe you can help me
to think about what do we need to
communicate to leaders executives you
know in in healthcare organizations
what's the right messaging that we need
to get to them because we've got to
reinforce the need to give back time I
think
yeah I mean there's multiple ways you
can kind of approach that you know one
of them is the through line is always
patient adherence right and preventing
readmissions or preventing bigger
complications because of non-adherence
which is a patient behavior right you're
you're depending on patient behavior for
that outcome and in order for that
outcome to happen the only way humans
are adherent to things is if we trust it
right that's one of the components now
I'm not talking about social
determinance of health and I'm not
talking about the complications of the
fragmented care they get. I'm talking
about the the one thing that is
[clears throat] it's a component that's
really important. When I had patients
who really felt that I cared for them
and the families knew I was there for
them, they would do 99% of the things I
asked them to do. Do this seven days, do
this three weeks, I need to see you back
in four weeks. Okay? And when they would
feel that compassion and empathy and
trust, they were more likely to trust me
would then trust my facility or hospital
and then put trust into the system,
right? And so when you have providers
who are spent as a leadership team, you
have those there is no I'm noting
anything. I I can probably say that
providers are all spent and a lot of
them are doing pajama time. I was one of
them. I would put my babies to sleep and
I would chart till 12:30, 1:00 a.m. And
the goal of that was not really the true
patient care for me to document. It was
for me to do the checklist for what was
required on the administrative side of
things to get that is it paid for,
right? And so from an executive
leadership team or a a leadership team,
it's about do the providers feel cared
for? Are they being seen as people? Are
we saying hey we want to put in
technologies not build something and
then intervene and put it in and it not
be done and then cause more confusion
and chaos. It's we want to take some
time to understand where your
administrative burdens are, where your
time sucks are, where you're being spent
in places rather than in your human
delivery. We want to go and study those.
We want to understand that and then we
want to go look at what technologies are
out there if any or is there something
we can do within our own systems and
supplement and enhance what we already
have to solve those problems. Right? And
then we're going to have a roll out to
add the intervention with your insights
as providers to put it in place and we
will reiterate it. Now the downfall of
that and most people are probably not
going to do what I'm saying because we
are in a race. The downfall to that is
that it requires organized structure and
time and that's where I feel that there
is going to be friction because the
leadership teams have their own goals to
obviously hit numbers for the business
you know not be in law whatever it may
be and the providers and the clinicians
and the nurses and the mas all of those
individuals are the flip side of that
are having to meet those demands right
and time unfortunately somehow time has
become our enemy when an actual uality.
I think time can actually be our friend
because we have less you work and less
money spent on fixing things that were
implemented too fast if we just
thoroughly executed the plan. Do you
know what I mean? So again, it may not
be realistic what I'm saying because of
the way the world is racing right now
with all that is going on, but I really
do feel the people that are getting lost
in this race are the ones who are
delivering the care and the ones who are
receiving the care. And that's a
problem.
That's such an important thing, too,
because we talk about this stuff so
sometimes like it's just mechanical,
right?
where we completely lose the lose our
our perspective when it comes to the
people who are delivering the care. You
work in the pediatric space. You are you
not supposed to feel anything and you're
taking care of children. I think you do,
right? I mean that's got to take its
toll and there's just more and more
pressure and then you step into a room
and you're looking at at a young child
who needs needs care.
You have to sit with that for a little
bit, right? and like really breathe into
what that means. And you know, we're not
when I see providers, one of the thing
that gives me hope is that the good of
humans is still there. No matter how
much pajama time a provider has, the
majority of providers are still going to
do their best in their hands to take
care of the child, for example. But the
other side to that is our elderly. We're
talking about elderly as if they don't
mean anything. And I'm generalizing what
I'm saying, but you know, when we talk
about like the technology is going to
scale and it's going to have thousands
of people on it and like at that point
what you've done is you've diminished
the sheer amount of individuals who have
paved the way for us to all be here and
the wisdom that they hold. We're
discounting and we're overlooking the
fact of who they are, right? Because
we're in a race. And when you're talking
about elderly, you're talking about
somebody's mom, somebody's grandmother,
someone who may have taken care of
others children's, someone who may have
moved four continents to come here and
has figured out, you know, paved a way
of life for generations to come. I mean,
this is what I'm talking about when I
mean the depth of human connection.
There is a space for technology. No
doubt I think that there is a space for
technology. I just don't want us missing
the point of what we're doing. You know,
you're talking about diagnosing a child
with cancer. I am sure there are lovely
ways and amazing innovative ways to
diagnose that cancer to
stage it to find it you know all the
things and that is incredible that we
can do something like that but in the
end we are still talking to someone's
child. we are still going to cut a human
being and we're still talking about
really putting in a massive stressor in
a family system in a world that is
already stressful. And so the these are
just like different components that I
give all of the credit to providers and
nurses and caregivers in the hospitals,
in clinics, in surgery centers. They are
pouring their heart out, especially when
they're tired. And that's something that
really drives my passion that are there
ways that I can help that. Are there
teams that I can go help that have the
technological knowhow but don't know
where to start in the clinical workflow?
Let's go solve that. Let's go give that
time back. And that's kind of where I
ignite a little bit in the in the
advisory roles or in the strategic roles
or even just start starting from ground
zero. Where do we start?
Chris, what do we do with this data and
putting our heads on that and create
creating an idea
to solve? There's so many ways you can
do that.
Yeah, you're you're so right. Never was
there a more transformational period of
you know for me in my life honestly it
was being in New York going through the
pandemic and you know I'm sure people
have heard this you know from many
angles you know you saw the best and the
worst of humanity in a situation like
that you know fortunately I've never met
a clinician yourself included who was
not 100% on on the same page when it
comes to the reason for what you do the
sacrifices that you make. It's all about
the individual that you're in front of
and you're trying to do something to
help someone get well or prevent them
from being sick. But I think the the the
human aspects of this when it comes to
the emotional side, I think that's the
piece that concerns me a little bit
because not only do we not talk about it
um in the context of the people who are
delivering care, but just in a general
sense, we're living in a world that's
going at Mach 10 with some of this
innovation, but there's a lot of other
things, a lot of other factors and
stresses that people are dealing with,
and they don't really in many cases have
the skills to to know how to even
navigate it.
Yeah. Um, you know, we you and I talked
a little bit about this, but I'd like to
explore with you if you don't mind. You
know, what are some of the factors that
make people feel uh inappropriate, you
know, from a clinician standpoint that
the burnout that they're dealing with
and what how do they determine whether
they should raise their hand and say, "I
need some help." I mean, how do how do
they deal with it? How do they cope? And
are there things that we should be doing
to try to put things in place to help
that?
Yeah. Um it's such an interesting space
and it's a much needed space. You know
when I uh after I finished my education
I went straight to the children's
hospital where there were children dying
right I mean they were dying because of
chronic illness terminally ill birth
defects whatever it may be but they were
dying and we didn't learn how to do that
per se. No one really taught us the ways
to maintain that and then turn around
after your 14 hour shift and come back
for another one. Like, you know, it's
it's one of those things. And what I
credit for me to get through that, I
credit the collective family that I had
that I worked with in the hospital.
Those nurses, those doctors that were on
the floor with me had been there some of
them two decades. I mean, they were
there for a very long time. And I have
to give sight and gratitude to the idea
that there are armies on those floors
who hold each other up when they lose
patients and they become a family. You
know, we would cry together. We would
hug families together and we would have
times of quiet, you know, where we would
all need space to really accept what
just happened. But I was fortunate
because I was in a time where I had
that. I don't know if everybody has
that. And right now what's happening is
I mean as a provider I would cry by
myself honestly because it was too much.
It was too daunting to say oh you need
to see more patients and in my mind and
all of us were thinking when where and
the hospitals were trying. I'm not
discounting that they were not. I think
that it was being done as a as kind of
like a general layer like oh we have
mental health services. Oh, we have
counselors through your benefits. But
when you're burdened in clinic and
you're working pajama time and you're
working on your weekends, who's going to
look for a therapist for you? Who how
are you going to have time for that?
Because you don't even have time for
your own children, right? I mean, I see
doctors who are racing to soccer games
and my biggest fear is that someone's
going to get into a car accident on the
way there, right? And so, there is a
huge burnout. There is a huge exhaustion
of the administrative load to be honest
with you. If you can decrease that the
the um digesting and accepting of the
things that happen to your patients, it
becomes a little bit more manageable to
grieve and to feel because you're not
grieving in exhaustion, right? Like that
compounds on itself quite honestly. And
so before, you know, doctors would hold
the hands of patients. They would fight
the idea that you need to hurry up. But
I worked with uh physicians who would
sit on the patient beds and hold the
patients hands and hug the moms and hug
the dads. And it didn't matter how late
it was going to be for them to go home.
That is just what they did. And so there
is opportunity to help nurses. There is
opportunity to help the clinical
assistance and medical assistance in
these hospitals and in these facilities.
They are the ones who are touching the
patients and they're going home not
equipped to turn that off and then go be
in home. Yes. Massive opportunity to
help support to help re-calibrate your
system. I mean, you're just in stress a
lot all day, right? And then you go home
and you're in another kind of stress,
right? And so the mental health
component is compounding and we're we're
having health issues because of it. You
know, providers are not always able to
maintain their physical and mental
health. Nurses are having issues with
that. When do we work out? When are when
do we have time to eat healthy? And
we're over we're overlooking these
things. It's it's a it's a complete
system, right? I can't solve all that by
myself, but there are there are things
that can be done to help support
individuals. So they don't have the
mental strain as much.
Yeah. And I think that there there's a
an acceptance and a normalization of
things that I think we've we've allowed
uh with all the pressure and all the the
race to innovate. And it's just
it's something we've got to try to
really kind of take a step back and
realize what we've done and fix this
because this is not just a small issue
that we could course correct with a a a
cool workflow. It's just not that
simple. We we really do have to focus on
creating that space. For an example, you
know, leaving one exam room and going
into another one to see another patient,
you're already behind schedule.
Yeah.
How when are you going to have a moment
to reset, right?
That's the basic thing that, you know,
we're just not we're not designing
anything that really helps with that.
And I I think there's a lot of
opportunities for us. And I love how
you're thinking about it. And I hope
that we can find some some other uh
people. I know there's there's a handful
that I've that I've met. I'm sure that
you have too. They'll probably be
excited to to find some things that are
really meaningful, but for goodness
sake, enough with the cool tech. That's
not what this is about, right? I mean,
yes, we want to do cool things, but it's
really got to be aimed at, you know,
improving the human experience. It has
to.
And it's not just one side of it or
another. It's just all of it. Um, if
you're going to do technology stuff and
that make that floats your boat,
awesome. Let's get let's put our heads
together and do something that's
actually going to help the people that
are needing care, the ones who are able
to deliver the care. But, you know, we
needed it by throwing more layers of
administrative tasks on it and he
keeping more pressure. It's not a
solution we could keep doing to people.
It's not
Yeah, I I 100% agree on that. And, you
know, a part of me is excited because of
the out-of-box thinking that
unfortunately I do sometimes or a lot of
the times. What it comes down to is that
it can be done
using the end goal which is giving the
the human component back. And a lot of
times when I'm building something or if
I'm advising on something or if I'm
problem solving so for something my end
goal is I imagine that it's like my
parent or my child. What do they need?
What do I need in those components? I'm
solving for that. I want that to be the
the image in my mind. all the time
because that is what is happening. We
are solving for someone's child, parent,
aunt, adult, grandparent, whatever it
is. In the end, we are solving for
humans and the the care component is not
going to go away. We have to deliver
care. The health of the nation is still
the health of the nation. Disregarding
how fast the technology is moving, we
still have a baby boomer population. we
still have a middle generation coming
and so I'm excited to see how AI can
help with those things, you know, help
kind of with preventative medicine and
like hopefully in the next generations
we can have less health care load, but
we still have the reality of our own
problem today,
right?
And I do feel like, you know, I'm like a
little kid in a playground because
there's so many things that you can do.
And if you love technology, what I would
say as an advice is pick one problem.
one problem in the workflow, one goal,
one thing. Because if you try to go
solve everything, there's too much to
solve, and you get lost in the universe
of things. And so, let's say you're
going to focus on I'm going to help my
families navigate their care, or I'm
going to help families consolidate their
information so that if they ever go to a
provider, they can give it to them. And
it's a it's a consolidated view of my
health so that my new provider can spend
time with me getting to know me with
full-on information. Right? So I think
being very focused on what you're
wanting to go and fix, you know, there's
companies out there who are working on
claims. I think that's a great place to
start, right? Like chasing claims,
chasing pending claims. Why is it
pending? Get the information, use AI to
go collect it. That's amazing. So that's
one that's one component of the whole
thing. So for me it's like I'm kind of
focusing on the human side of things and
where is it that my mind can help in the
technology to then give back that right
and so yeah.
Yeah that's actually
that's something that just you just ded
when you're saying that there's a
strategic side of this that we got to we
have to think about too. And if you're
head of an organization and you know
that you've got some burnout issues and
they're both in the nursing area as well
as the the
you know all clinicians essentially
there's probably other support staff
that are dealing with it too. But we
also know that there's a global shortage
of nursing. There's also a shortage in
in a lot of specialties. If people are
seeing this kind of load, what's the
incentive to want to go to school to
become a clinician?
Yeah,
we have to think differently about this.
This is not just, you know, how fast can
we get the technology in there? Can we
be more efficient? Can we, you know,
make things somehow more tolerable? No,
we're talking about a an ecosystem
that's been eroding basically because
we've just been focused on the
efficiency stuff and the and the in the
technology thing. I mean that's not I
want to oversimplify it but I think you
understand where I'm going with it.
Yeah.
Why would someone want to go into one of
these professions if this is the way
it's going to be?
Yeah. And you know it's funny because I
saw some chatter someone had posted like
oh AI can help some you know help a
therapist see five times more patient or
five yeah 5x patients in a month. And
the chatter was therapists responding
like who said that we can see 5x
patients in a month, right? Do I agree
that it will help us be more efficient
from the administrative things that we
do? 100%. I think that there are lots of
ways to help that. What I don't think
the goal is is for people to see more
people so that we can get more revenue
and so that we can, you know what I
mean? And so I think that again the goal
and the mission of what the initiative
is needs to be realistic in the sense of
like is this really going to help my
providers? Like is this really going to
help my clinicians? Like looking at that
because I'm going to tell you the
burnout is real. And if we start losing
amazing clinicians in our health care
spaces, we will not deliver care the way
that we've always known how we do. and
and there is people out there doing
amazing health care and providing
services, but if we don't plan for that,
we're going to not have those people and
they're going to leave, right? Or
they're going to retire early or they're
going to, I don't know, go figure out
another way of giving care or figuring
out another way to make an income
because people's passion when they come
into this space is not just money. It is
really it it takes special people to do
what they do. And I'm I'm not even
including myself. All the people that I
worked with, all the people that I watch
now, all the people who are doing
surgeries, all the paramedics, everybody
who is giving themselves to help others,
it takes a very special passion and
calling to do that. And we need to build
systems that honor that because if we
don't, it's going to diminish and we'll
lose kind of those angels that are that
are in the world to to help bring light
to those who are needing it, you know.
Yeah. I don't want to I don't want to
make people feel horrible. I know some
of their stuff is a little bit heavy
that we're talking about. But I think
it's important though just to have the
context and the understanding of what
the what's really going on so that we
really start to dial in our thinking
around what are we really going to solve
for and what's really going to be
meaningful. And you know from that
perspective there's a lot of things to
be optimistic about. And I know I've
seen a few things and they, you know,
I'd love to, you know, hear from your
perspective some of the things that
you've seen that, you know, that that
are exciting that maybe we haven't paid
enough attention to that we should be.
Yeah. You know, I really think that
there's a a lot of companies out there
who are doing this AI scribing, which
has been a thing before, but now there's
like layers on top of that that like
help summarize information, pull out
pertinent data, lay information for a
provider so that they can, you know,
consolidate that and have a summary
while they're talking to the patients.
So, they're not typing as much, right?
because they are actually able to look
at the patient and speak instead of
sitting at a computer and like typing on
the screen and the patient's kind of
behind the computer. You're not really
looking at them. So, I think that's
rooms myself.
Yeah. The diagnostic things. I mean, I'm
super excited about the fact that
they're using these technologies in
diagnostics. I mean, the amount of
people that you're going to find who
have something that may have been
overlooked and like can actually speed
up their care and speed up the way that
they can um recover. Like those are all
and this is why I'm excited. I I am very
excited in the idea of using these
technologies to get ahead of things, to
catch things earlier, to not have stage
four cancer. Or can you imagine a world
where like patients don't have stage
four cancer and we catch it at stage one
like those are all very exciting things
and there's so many things I mean you
have GI disease you have endocrinology
at whole sector in itself you have
metabolic disorders you have
cardiovascular the amount of opportunity
there is in order to help kind of the
outcomes of patient care and patient
outcomes for the nation as a whole maybe
the world as a That's really exciting
stuff. Like I'm really excited about
that. I think where we have to focus
though is you still have to have
delivery of care if that's the way we're
going and we're not going to use AI to
like talk to patients because I have a
feeling that my 80-year-old grandmother
may not talk to a robot openly. And I
may be wrong. She may not talk to an AI
openly if she had a human. She might
she's going to pick the human probably
because that's what they've known.
That's how they've grown. that's how
they've generationally done things. So
the it's just I think the through line
is just not forgetting that we're
solving who we're solving for, why we're
solving for it, and what are we doing
like what are we doing it for? Right? So
I do have a lot of excitement about it.
I mean I'm playing all the time to see
how is it that we can make it better.
What really is serves and something that
just popped in my head. One of the
things that's very difficult is that you
know I can come up with a lot of ideas
to solve the gaps within a clinical
workflow for example. But I can't throw
five apps at a provider who has 50
patients to see in a day that has to do
50 charts in an EMR and then go sign
into another platform and do one thing
and then go sign into another platform
and do one thing. And so if we can move
into a world where it can be
consolidated with an EMR, there are
compliance rules that allow those types
of things. That would be very helpful,
right? And so that co goes into like
regulations,
compliance, that's a whole another
world. But do the EMRs want that type of
help? Do those companies want to open
the gateway and say, "Yes, we like these
ideas. You can implement your software
within our universe of EMR. Maybe that
will happen. Maybe it's happening now.
But consolidating the use of the
technology in one system that the
providers are using or the clinicians
are using would be very beneficial.
Yeah, it seems like we've been talking
about interoperability for a very very
long time. But it's been very very slow
to say the least.
Yeah. You know, there has been, you
know, there certainly has been some
legislation and appending for quite a
while now that would at least force the
sharing of information, you know, at
least when it comes time for treatment,
right?
So that, you know, the data would be
made available, you know, the minute you
are, if you're a physician, the minute
you're going to be treating a patient,
you should have access to all that
information. That's the the premise of
it. But it doesn't seem to be moving at
the clip that it should. I I kind of
thought that maybe they made a mistake
even talking about it because it sounded
like the right thing,
right?
But but it it is a it's still an issue
that we got to figure we got to figure
out how to solve for it. It's not it's
not easy because there's so much there's
so much red tape and
yeah,
there's regulatory things that are
different in every state. There's just a
lot of barriers. But that's why people
like us need to put our heads together.
Yeah. lock arms, find some more people,
and really go after this hard. Like you
said, remember why we're doing it
because there's a lot we can do. We just
we have to apply ourselves to the right
things, right?
And we're some of that means that people
are going to have to push on to leaders
honestly because there this is this is
too important. You know, I talk a little
bit about the erosion of trust that's
that exists. Everyone knows inherently
today if you're if you're paying
attention there's been trust breaking
going on for a long time and it's not
not something that we think about
deliberately. It's just that the
environment that we're in it it's just
been so overrun with technology that
people aren't relating to one another
like they used to. And so you know
you're you're just
being lulled to sleep a little bit and
all of a sudden you realize that oh I
thought they trusted me and no they they
don't. Yeah, you know, if you're a CEO,
the stats are not pretty and your
engagement scores might be really,
really good. But what I look at in the
middle of when I was looking at the when
I look at engagement, I don't worry
about the stuff on the top end because
of course you all you all want to hear
the positive.
And of course, we want to deal with the
things that are on the bottom end too.
But the piece that's really really
frightening to me is when people don't
have are not motivated to even move the
needle.
Yes.
To give you a positive or a negative.
And and that to me is that that's really
the part you want to be paying attention
to because if you have a lot of space in
the middle, you really got to dig in to
understand why.
Yeah.
And a lot of it comes down to people
need to be able to trust and it's needs
to happen at every layer when it comes
to how an organization runs. If you want
to do technology things, you want to do
these kind of initiatives and also make
sure that we're supporting the mission.
We really need to remember that this is
this is entirely about humanity and and
caring for people. It's got to start
there and it has to stay on that and we
have to apply ourselves to the things
that really undergur you know the
mission of patient care and you know we
first do know her right and that's not
that's not something we talk about
enough outside of a you know a a
clinical care type of perspective but I
think as a nonclinian I need to take
that to heart too I mean are we building
things that are helping or not and if
it's adding more burden more layers that
that's that's not a good answer so a lot
we can do there. We need to do better.
Yeah.
Um you know, we're kind of getting
getting close to the time um on this on
our show today, but if we can look ahead
uh maybe in the next, you know, few
months, you know, thinking about some of
the things that you've been working on,
what you may be aware of, I'd love to
hear hear your thoughts around what what
do you think we could tackle reasonably
if we can some smart people together,
they're actually passionate, what could
we do? then maybe talk about where you
see things over the next 12 to 18 months
as well. I would go further than that,
but the technology is accelerating so
fast. It's probably things we can solve
tomorrow that we don't even know where
we
Yeah, I think um you know to touch on a
little bit what you were talking about
about the trust erosion. I think there
is opportunities in coming back to
empathetic leadership and starting from
the top empathetic leadership. when I
came into the clinical world and what I
was seeing um when we were in training
is that the leadership was present, the
leadership was around, the leadership
was open to questions, they were very
involved because they had done the work
before. They were clinical. They had had
their hands in there. They had seen the
long days. They had seen, you know, a
patient code at the end of your shift
and you had to stay till 11:00 at night
even though you were at the hospital at
6:00 a.m. They had seen all of those
things. And there was always an a layer
and again this is I'm talking about my
experience where I grew up as a
clinician and provider, but there was a
layer of empathy that kind of ran
through the creation of goals and the
driving of goals. And now more than
ever, because of the burnout, because of
being tired, because people are
overwhelmed with noise of of information
and the fear that's happening,
empathetic leadership is necessary and
we have to build trust again. And that's
and that's another component that I
would love to have my hands in. As a
leader, I was very firm. These are what
the things we have to do today. These
are your goals for the week. You will
not be late. You know, there are certain
pillars of trust that you have to meet
in order for me to give you autonomy to
go and do your job. And that empathetic
leadership is required. Revisiting your
mission statement and your assuming or
assessing your culture more than ever is
needed more frequently than ever because
the world is changing just like you
said. And so I think there's an
opportunity right now to go back and
build that empathy again. remembering
why we're doing it and what we're doing
it for. And my outlook in the next, you
know, 12 to 18 months and where I kind
of get excited is like projects that
will help my mind kind of goes to
consolidating information, presenting
information in ways that's a summary
style for families and providers. So,
it's kind of like your kind of pocket of
this is me, this is my health, I'm
having these issues right now. And so
the provider or clinician doesn't have
to call a PCP's office and call the O
and call the ortho specialist to go get
all of the information and then build a
story. That is kind of where I think is
where I kind of find passion because I
I've been in so many scenarios and so
many experiences as a provider, as a
mom, as a daughter, a daughter-in-law,
now a niece. You know, I'm helping my
aunt navigate cancer right now and it is
a beating because I'm a clinician and
reading all the notes.
Yeah.
I can't imagine a 75year-old individual
reading six notes from six different
people with six different directions on
what to do on what day when. It is quite
frankly overwhelming. And so where I see
myself in the next few months is working
with teams who are maybe thinking about
doing something like that so that I can
help kind of put in the little seeds of
like these are the things that would be
very helpful, right? And in 12 to 18
months, I think that there's going to be
a lot of individuals who are going to
create some cool ideas and hopefully
have the sandbox to help implement it
and test it. And I'm hoping that like
more and more cool things like come out
that way and the exhaustion and burnout
kind of diminishes a little bit and the
trust and empathy starts coming up and I
think there is a world for that. We just
have to do it properly.
Well, I I can speak for myself. I am
happy to tag team with you and help you
be supportive in any way I can for for
what you're what you're doing. I think
it's it's incredibly important. And just
to reinforce your your point on empathy,
two things I'll say. There is some
really cool technology that has been
developed by some some really brilliant
people and clinicians out out in
California. And I'm sure you and I will
talk a little bit more about it cuz I
think there could be some fun things
that we might be able to do to to help
bring some of that technology to places
where it's not likely to get if we can't
solve for things from a financial
standpoint. But that's a whole another
thing. The empathy thing I really want
to just want to encourage people to
think about this because we're not
talking about just you at the sea level.
There are people that are managing your
teams and at the very first level a
supervisor whatever their title is
that's not the important thing. We need
to make sure that your management
training actually has some sections and
components in there that are really
teaching how to be empathetic and what
are the signs that you need to do it
when you're working with human beings.
It's just really important and I think
it's overlooked a lot, but there's
there's never been a a bigger need for
that right now than there is right now.
At least from what I'm sensing and I I
don't know if you agree with that.
I agree with that. And I you know the
way I always lead it's I always look at
somebody and I and again I go back to
the same thing like it is somebody's
mother it is someone's daughter it is
someone's sister and more than looking
at what they're doing wrong it's
understanding what they're doing number
one.
Yeah.
Taking the time to understand is there a
knowledge gap that they just didn't
understand it and really teasing out
these critical questions. Right. Are
they not doing it because they're
stressed because their child is sick and
like their child is just a babysitter
that they found on the internet the
night before because they were desperate
to find somebody for a shift. These are
the types of things especially I mean
this could go anywhere but in healthcare
especially you're talking about a let's
say let's take the example of a nurse
you know you're talking about a nurse
who's coming to take care four of four
or five very sick patients in the
hospital
who let their sick child at home who may
not have found someone that they 100%
trusted but they needed to take the
shift right
so I always remembered that I'm with
individuals who have the same stressors
that our patients have And so we have to
be very mindful of these things. We have
to be mindful of the noise. We have to
be mindful that people are overwhelmed
right now. And we really need to take a
pulse of where our team is individually,
not just collectively. And that takes
time for a manager. You have to take a
lot of the admin lift. They have to
regularly meet. They have to regularly
report. Right? So
right
there is um empathy is something
that if we can have tools and workflows
and I don't even want to say workflows
but opportunities to inject empathy
again into these spaces it will
tremendously bring an advantage to what
we're doing.
Yeah it's it's so needed. I mean, it it
really is, you know, you don't have to
take too many steps outside your front
door or don't you can't turn on social
media or or a television and not see
that there's a need for this. So,
I really appreciate you your attention
to that as we're wrapping up our
conversation today. And again, I can't
thank you enough. I really do appreciate
that you take the took the time to come
on and have this conversation. and
excited to talk more with you because I
think there's just so much more that we
can do and certainly conversations that
need to continue to be pushed so that
the the clinical and human views both of
those things stay in focus and we don't
let this just be a technology thing and
and
maybe maybe we can actually have the
kind of impact that we we intend and the
technology will serve humanity the way
it should not the other way around. So
again, thank you so much for coming on
this show and I look forward to working
with you again and let's find some
things we can tag team and we'll we'll
rally some troops and we'll do some good
things together.
Yeah, let's do it. You know, I'm I'm
hopeful maybe I'm, you know, too much in
the rainbows and unicorn world. I But I
do feel um the good the spirit of us
will collectively do good. And so we can
use the technology, we can create things
and ideas and I and I do have a lot of
faith in the fact that that we can do it
and there are ways to do that. So my
intention is to help as much as possible
and to increase our empathy and really
look at what we're doing and take care
of everything um in the sense of our
providers, clinicians, any staff that is
working in these places that then
deliver our care. It is a very big
spectrum of folks and there I would love
to continue conversations of how we can
create ways to help that innovate and
utilize technologies to to take off
burdens. Yeah, I will welcome those
conversations and ideas, you know,
strategies anytime.
Uh we I'll make sure that you you have
all the information that you need in the
show notes to be able to reach out to
Poonam if you want to have one of these
conversations there. She's not uh
lacking in passion or ideas. I I you're
somebody who's looking to to solve some
real problems. I think this would be a
smart move for you to reach out to
Ponam. And that's going to do it for
this episode of the Signal Room. Really
appreciate you all for listening. Stay
calm, stay human.
Thank you.
That's it for this episode of the Signal
Room. If today's conversation sparked
something in you, an idea, a challenge,
or perspective worth amplifying, I'd
love to hear from you. Message me on
LinkedIn or visit cigarroompodcast.com
to explore being a guest on an upcoming
episode. Until next time, stay tuned,
stay curious, and stay human.